<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pages on Force of Life</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/en/page/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Pages on Force of Life</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <managingEditor>Zhixiao-Zhang@outlook.com (Patrick)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>Zhixiao-Zhang@outlook.com (Patrick)</webMaster>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 09 Sep 2023 17:09:20 +0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/en/page/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>About Me</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Sep 2023 17:09:20 +0800</pubDate>
      <author>Zhixiao-Zhang@outlook.com (Patrick)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/about/</guid>
      
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hello!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m Patrick Zhang, a software engineering student at Sichuan University in China. I&amp;rsquo;m a fan of systems (you can check this category through &lt;a href=&#34;https://csrankings.org/&#34;&gt;csrankings&lt;/a&gt;), especially in the field of programming language (compiler and program analysis), computer architecture, and operating systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My favorite software is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.vim.org/&#34;&gt;vim&lt;/a&gt;, which is a powerful text editor. And I&amp;rsquo;m a fan of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bram_Moolenaar&#34;&gt;Bram Moolenaar&lt;/a&gt;, the author of vim, who has already pass away in 2023. I want to write a software which make a difference to the whole world like vim in my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the english version site, I usually write cs-related blogs (especially about compiler), if you want to read more my personal thinking, you can change to the chinese site by click the &lt;code&gt;中文&lt;/code&gt;. If you meet any problems related to my articles or just want to chat with me, feel free to  &lt;a href=&#34;zhixiao-zhang@outlook.com&#34;&gt;email to me&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:zhixiao-zhang@outlook.com&#34;&gt;zhixiao-zhang@outlook.com&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;environment&#34;&gt;Environment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have two laptops, a Macbook Air M1 and a second-hand ThinkPad T480 to provide x86-64.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like Linux at most, because it is an open-source operating system. I can do whatever I want to do on it. I find it&amp;rsquo;s convenient to write code on linux, because it&amp;rsquo;s easy to set the environment by the package manager. Moreover, my favorite distribution is gentoo linux, which is a source-based distribution. I like the moment when I compile the software by myself, and it can be relatively stable compared to arch linux which is also the rolling release. However, I use Debian on my laptop now, because I wanna save time to do other things, and more importantly, save the electricity bill lol. Debian is a comparable stable and extremely powerful distribution, it&amp;rsquo;s easy to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use Macbook Air M1 as my main laptop, because it&amp;rsquo;s stable, and maintain a great balance between development and life. It&amp;rsquo;s posix compliant, but its default animation is more smooth and UI design is more beautiful than Linux. Though I use Windows when I was a child, I don&amp;rsquo;t like it, because it usually dumps, and it&amp;rsquo;s not stable. But I still use it to play games and use some softwares which only support Windows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;education&#34;&gt;Education&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2021.09 - now, Sichuan University, Software Engineering, Bachelor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(To be continued)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
